Guide to the Alvin Howard Sanders Papers, circa 1839-1925.
Sanders, Alvin Howard Papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Alvin Howard Sanders papers, circa 1839-1925.
6312
Sanders, Alvin Howard, 1860-1948.
1.5 Cubic Feet.
Correspondence, Newspapers, Photographs, Printed Materials, Publications.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Photographs, correspondence, drawings, clippings, reports, financial records, awards, journals, articles, and other material pertaining to and deriving from Sanders' editorship of The Breeder's Gazette, his work in livestock breeding, and his authorship of several books on agricultural persons and subjects.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Alvin Howard Sanders (1860-1948) was the son of James Harvey Sanders, a renowned livestock author and founder of the leading livestock journal, The Breeder's Gazette.
Alvin attended Cornell University in Ithaca, New York from 1878 to 1879. His father, then editor of the National Livestock Journal in Chicago called upon his son to help him in the editorial office. In 1881, Alvin graduated from the Union College of Law and received his license from the state of Illinois in 1882.
James Sanders founded The Breeder's Gazette in Chicago on December 1, 1881. Alvin decided to join his father in his new endeavor and was employed on the staff as co-editor. He married Elizabeth A. Hildebrand of Chicago on April 25, 1882. By 1892, Alvin had become editor and owner of The Breeder's Gazette.
On February 20, 1900, the Senate confirmed the appointment of Alvin Sanders as a member of the American delegation to the Paris Exposition.
Atter the Union Stock Yards opened in Chicago, Arthur G. Leonard, Robert Ogilvie, and Alvin Sanders formed the Saddle and Sirloin Club located at the Stockyard Inn in 1903. On the club walls were portraits of the important persons in the livestock movement. In Alvin's book, At the Sign of the Stock Yard Inn, he wrote about the lives of Robert Bakewell, Thomas Bates, Amos Cruickshank and others.
On August 16, 1905, a convention was held at the Illinois Theater in Chicago which was attended by leading commercial and agricultural organizations. It was here that the American Reciprocal Tariff League was formed. Alvin was elected chairman and held this position until 1909. During his service, he corresponded with President Theodore Roosevelt regarding foreign trade agreements with the United States.
President William Taft appointed a Tariff Board in September 1909 which included Henry C. Emery, professor at Yale; James B. Reynolds, Assistant Secretary of Treasury; and Alvin Sanders.
Alvin wrote many livestock books which included such works as A History of Aberdeen- Angus Cattle, Red White and Roan, Short-Horn Cattle, and The Story of the Herefords. In 1917, he published in collaboration with Wayne Dinsmore, A History of the Percheron Horse. The French government awarded him with the Cross of Officer Merite Agricole in appreciation for his work.
Over the years, he was awarded many awards and honors. He received the degree of Doctor of Agriculture from the University of Illinois in 1906. In 1911, he was presented with the Honorary Degree of Doctor of Laws from Kenyon College. Alvin was also awarded the Chevalier of the Order of Leopold from the King of Belgium for his contribution in promoting interest in scientific stock breeding.
He was a member of many different agricultural organizations. He was made president of the Saddle and Sirloin Club in 1915. Governor Frank O. Lowden appointed him a member of the Illinois Board of Agricultural Advisors in 1917.
Alvin Sanders retired from The Breeder's Gazette journal in 1927. The livestock journal continued to be published by different editors until it went out of business in 1964.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Photographs, correspondence, drawings, clippings, reports, financial records, awards, journals, articles, and other material pertaining to and deriving from Sanders' editorship of The Breeder's Gazette, his work in livestock breeding, and his authorship of several books on agricultural persons and subjects.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Sanders, Alvin Howard, 1860-1948.; Saddle and Sirloin Club.
Titles:
The Breeders' Gazette.
Subjects:
Livestock--Development.; Livestock exhibitions.; Livestock improvement.; Cattle breeders.; Agriculture--Social aspects.; Agriculture law and legislation.; Agriculturists.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Graphic Material
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Assorted Files
CONTAINER LIST
- Graphic Material
  - Booth's home, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Killerby Hall in 1915. Old home of Thomas and John Booth.
  - Bruce's home, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Robert Bruce home, Ireland.
    Ireland
  - Grinnell farm, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Managers residence on the Locust Valley farm of Russell Grinnell. Robert F. Hildebrand, photographer of Landscapes and animals, NY.
    Exeter, Rhode Island
  - Woodburn house, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Woodburn house, Kentucky.
    Kentucky
  - Bates home, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Home of Thomas Bates at Kirklevinqton.
  - Collinq Home, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Robert Collinq home, Barmpton, County Durham.
    Barmpton, England
  - Stone Stable, Ladykirk, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The big stone stable at Ladykirk. W. Green, Berwick.
    Ladykirk
  - Miller, Minnie Hampshire sheep, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Mrs. Minnie W. Miller Hampshire sheep, Proprietess Thousand Springs Farm, Wendell, Idaho. Livestock Photo Co.
    Wendell, Idaho
  - London Central Markets, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    London Central Markets.
    London, England
  - Pasture scene a t L.C. Emmons, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Pasture scene L.C. Emmons, Swarthmore, PA. H.A. Strohmeyer, Jr., Photographer of animals, NY.
    Swarthmore, Pennsylvania
  - Thousand Springs farm, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Thousand Springs farm, Wendell, Idaho. Guernsey cattle and a few of the springs. Livestock Photo Co.
  - Milking cows, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Milking cows in village of Carantin, France. Photo by J.E. Wing
    Carantin, France
  - Saddle and Sirloin Club, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Interior room at the Saddle and Sirloin Club, Chicago.
    Chicago, Illinois
  - Saddle and Sirloin Club, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Saddle and Sirloin Club, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - International Live Stock Exposition, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    International Live Stock Exposition building, front exterior view.
  - Indiana pig and boy, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Indiana pig club boy getting in training for the show. J.G. Allen, West Lafayette, IN.
    Indiana
  - Jos. E. Wing and Perry G. Holden, 1913-12-18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Mr. Joseph E. Wing and Prof. Perry G. Holden discussing their mutually favorite topic, alfalfa. Breeders Gazette (frontispiece).
  - Championship cattle bred by T.A. Russell, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photo & brief history of Flower Girl 18th & Missie of Downsview cattle bred by T.A. Russell, Downsview.
  - Barn Sketch by Joseph E. Wing, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sketch of a barn for feeding 1000 lambs and a written proposal by Joseph E. Wing.
  - William Burlton portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Portrait of William Burlton.
    Norway, Iowa
  - Hon. T. C. Jones portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Portrait of Hon. T.C. Jones, Associate editor of National Livestock Journal. Bodurthas Studio, Sandusky.
  - James Howie portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Portrait of James Howie. McGregor Studio, Kilmarnock, Scotland.
  - Lord Fitzhardinge portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    The Late Lord Fitzhardinge.
  - William Warfield portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    William Warfield, famous Shorthorn breeder who owned Grasmere near Lexington, KY, wrote the first American text on stock breeding. Mullen Studio, Lexington, KY.
  - L.N. Bonhan portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Portrait of L.N. Bonhan.
  - A.M. Garland portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Portrait of A.M. Garland. Brands Studios, Chicago.
  - Captain Barclay portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Captain Barclay walking 1000 miles in 1000 hours. Capt. Barclay of Ury, the father of Shorthorn breeding in North Scotland.
    Scotland
  - J.G. Imbodeu portrait, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Portrait of J.G. Imbodeu. Vandeventer Studio.
    Decatur, Illinois
  - C.A. Lewis portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Portrait of C.A. Lewis.
  - John Ashton portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Portrait of John Ashton.
  - F. D. Coburn portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Portrait of Foster Dwight Coburn. Secretary of the Kansas State Board of Agriculture at Topeka. Editor of the Livestock Indicator of Kansas City. Author of the Book of Alfalfa.
  - Geo. C. Morrow portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Portrait of Geo. C. Morrow.
  - Amos Cruickshank portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Portrait of Amos Cruickshank. Famous Scottish breeder of Shorthorn cattle in the 1800's. E. Geering, Aberdeen.
  - Edward N. Wentworth portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Portrait of Edward N. Wentworth. Director of the Livestock Bureau for Armour & Co. He also served on the Breeder's Gazette staff. Also, served on faculties of Iowa and Kansas State colleges. Author of The Portrait Gallery of the Saddle and Sirloin Club.
  - E.T. Robbins portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Portrait of E.T. Robbins.
  - Hon. James Wilson portrait, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Portrait of Hon. James Wilson, Secretary of the US Department of Agriculture.
    Washington, DC
  - Alvin Howard Sanders portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Portrait of Alvin Howard Sanders. Livestock Journalist, editor of the Breeders Gazette and subject of this collection. P.H. Alusragh, Chicago.
  - John Cochrane portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Portrait of John Cochrane. McGregor & Sons, Kilmarnock.
  - A.S. Alexander portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Portrait of A. S. Alexander. DeTonge, Madison, Wisconsin
  - W.A. Henry portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Portrait of William Arnon Henry. Cornell University, 1880, and Dean of College of Agriculture, University of Wisconsin. S.L. Stein, Milwaukee.
  - Will Barnes portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Portrait of Will Barnes. Harris & Ewing.
  - Andrew Allan portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Andrew Allan, 1823-1898, Wunnoch, Dalry, Ayrshire
  - Andrew Allan, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Biography of Andrew Allan.
  - Armour Portrait, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Armour Portrait Ready for Place in Hall of Fame.
  - Philip D. Armour portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Portrait of Philip D. Armour. Founder of the Armour Meat Packing Company, Chicago. Brisbois, Chicago.
  - Michael Logan, 1913-03-01 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Death of Noted Agriculturist, Mr. Michael Logan of Bargenoch.
    Bargenoch, Scotland
  - Michael Logan portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Portrait of Michael Logan.
  - Earl of Coventry portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Earl of Coventry, noted Hereford Breeder.
    England
  - Lord Coventry, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Donation of Lord Coventry's photo.
    Wimbledon, England
  - Philip D. Armour, 1914-01-28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Address by Alvin H. Sanders, D. Agr. L.L.D., editor of the Breeders Gazette, at the Univ of Illinois, Jan 28, 1914.
  - Philip D. Armour portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Portrait of Philip D. Armour in the Illinois Farmers' Hall of Fame, University of Illinois.
  - Amos Cruickshank portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Photo of an oil painting of Amos Cruickshank, famous Scottish breeder of Shorthorn Cattle. This painting was done from a photo taken by Alvin Sanders when he called on Mr. Cruickshank in Scotland and is believed to have been the last photo taken of him.
  - Mrs. John Clay, 1923-09-27 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Eulogy of Mrs. John Clay including her portrait and her only son, John Clay, Jr.
    Woodstock, Canada
  - Mrs. John Clay and John Clay, Jr. portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Portrait of "Jack" Clay and his mother, Mrs. John Clay
  - Samuel R. Guard portrait, 1929-10-03 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Portrait of Samuel R. Guard. He took over the Breeders Gazette in 1927.
  - Philander C. Knox portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Group photo of Alvin Sanders (right), Mrs. Sanders (middle), & Secretary of State, Philander Knox (left).
    Palm Beach, Florida
  - Joseph E. Wing portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Portrait of Joseph E. Wing, writer for the Breeders Gazette.
  - Amos Cruickshank, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Portrait of Amos Cruickshank for the Breeders Gazette issue of Christmas 1909.
  - Earl of Dunmore portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Portrait of Earl of Dunmore.
  - Notice of Auction, 1872, 1875, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Catalogue of the Improved Short Horned Cattle, bred by the Earl of Dunmore, sold by auction.
    Dunmore, England
  - William A. Harris portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Bronze bust of the late US Senator William A. Harris. Erected on the campus of the Kansas Agricultural College at Manhattan.
  - Residence of John Clay, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Residence of John Clay in Scotland.
  - Cattle, "Model Mill (?)", Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    "Model Mill (?)" at her new home at Baker S.H. Farms.
    Kansas City, Missouri
  - Bull, "Lonton Knight", 1928-01-01 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Dutchie Webster bought this bull from the Prince of Wales.
  - Shorthorn cattle, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Shorthorns at Buckland Hill Farm.
    Nokesville, Virginia
  - Cattle, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Cattle at Babraham, Cambridge
  - Heifer, "Estelle of Maisemore", Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Smithfield Fat Stock Show. Aberdeen Angus Heifer "Estelle of Maisemore" J J Cridlan, 1st Breed Cup & Champion beast of the show.
  - Shorthorn bull, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    The $60,000.00 Shorthorn bull.
  - Shorthorn, "Third Duke of Hillhurst", 1872 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    "Third Duke of Hillhurst" purchased Sep 1872 by the Earl of Dunmore for 1000 guineas and her pedigree.
  - Hereford ox, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Bred by Mr R. Hill… property of the Earl of Warwick, exhibited at the Smithfield Cattle Show 1839.
  - Hereford ox, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Bred by John Buckley...
  - Hereford ox, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Bred by H Chamberlain... exhibited at the Smithfield Show 1838. Engraved for the Farmers Magazine.
  - Cattle & sheep in Scotland, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Letter and photos of sheep & cattle of Scotland.
  - Two Ayrshire cows, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Letter and three Ayrshire cow photos from C.L. Burlingham, Sec., Ayrshire Breeders Association.
    Brandon, Vermont
  - Belted Galloway Cows, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Photos of Belted Galloway Cows for the New Breeders Gazette.
  - Bronze tablet Saddle and Sirloin Club, Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Bronze tablet which was on the Saddle and Sirloin Club of Chicago.
  - Clydesdale Horse Headquarters, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Clydesdale Horse Headquarters which was at the Stockyards in Chicago.
  - Arthur Leonard portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Portrait of Arthur Leonard. President of the Union Stock Yards. A founder of the International Livestock Exposition.
  - Thomas E. Wilson portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Portrait of Thomas E. Wilson, President of the Wilson Meat Packing Company.
  - Calvin Coolidge portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Portrait of President Calvin Coolidge.
  - Joseph E. Wing portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Portrait of Joseph E. Wing
  - Frank D. Tomson portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Portrait of Frank D. Tomson, breeder of Shorthorn cattle.
  - DeWitt C. Wing, Undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Portrait of DeWitt C. Wing.
  - William R. Goodwin portrait, 1916-08-01 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Portrait of William R. Goodwin, vice president of the Sanders Publishing Co., managing editor of the Breeders Gazette.
  - Nicholas Longworth portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Portrait of Nicholas Longworth.
  - Robert A (?), Undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Farming scenes, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Boards containing farming scenes.
  - Tariff Board, Undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Photo of the Tariff Board.
  - Franklin MacVeagh portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Portrait of Franklin MacVeagh, Secretary of the Treasury.
  - William Taft portrait, 1910-12-23 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Portrait of President William H. Taft.
  - Philander Knox portrait, 1912-07-02 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Portrait of Secretary of State Philander Knox.
  - Nelson W. Aldrich portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Senator Nelson W. Aldrich architect of the Payne-Aldrich Tariff Act- (1909).
  - Henry C. Emery portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Portrait of Henry Emery, professor at Yale and member of the Tariff Board, Washington, DC.
  - James B. Reynolds portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Portrait of James Reynolds, Asst. Secretary of the Treasury and a member of the Tariff Board, Washington, DC.
  - Frank O. Lowden portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Portrait of Frank Lowden, governor of Illinois (1917-1921).
  - John Clay portrait, Undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Portrait of John Clay, president of the International Live Stock Exposition, and contributing writer for the Breeders Gazette.
  - Various Journal Articles, Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Various Journal articles by Alvin Sanders.
  - Richard J. Oglesby, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Portrait of Richard Oqlesby, governor of Illinois and US Senator (1873).
  - Philander C. Knox portrait, Undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Portrait of Philander C. Knox.
  - Cover of the 1st issue of The Breeder's Gazette, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Cover of the front page of The Breeder's Gazette, Vol. 1, No. 1, Chicago, Dec 1, 1881.
- Correspondence
  - Letters of Correspondence, 1900-1915 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Correspondence to and from Alvin Sanders, 1900 - 1915.
  - Letters of Correspondence, 1916-1923 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Correspondence to and from Alvin Sanders, 1916 - 1923.
  - Letters of Correspondence, 1924-1946 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Correspondence to and from Alvin Sanders, 1924 - 1946.
  - Jack London, Undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Jack London correspondence, photos, and newspaper clipping.
  - Tariff Board, 1905-1912 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Correspondence, clippings and reports of the Tariff Board
- Assorted Files
  - Breeder's Gazette financial records, Undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Breeder's Gazette Journal financial records.
  - Awards of Alvin Sanders, Undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Awards presented to Alvin Sanders.
  - "The Cry of the Hounds", Undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Article for publication by John Clay.
  - Material & photos from Joe Wing, Undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Articles & photos for publication by Joe Wing.
  - Agricultural Journals & Newspapers, Undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Agricultural Journals & Newspapers
  - Agricultural Journals & Newspapers, Undated (Box 3, Folder 44)